Guide to the John O'Hara Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John O'Hara papers
1934-1970
YCAL MSS 729
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes)
The papers document a portion of the creative process of writer John O'Hara, 1905-1970. They consist primarily of typed manuscript drafts, galley proofs, and page proofs of individual short stories, collections of stories, and novels, many with manuscript annotations. Some drafts of the collections include previously-printed stories excised from their original print source (often the New Yorker ). The manuscript for "The Ewings" is a photocopy. There is also a small amount of correspondence between O'Hara, James T. Babb, and Robert Hawthorne Wylie. The papers span the range of much of O'Hara's career, from circa 1934 to circa 1970, but represent only a portion of his creative output.
O'Hara, John, 1905-1970
John O'Hara, 1905-1970
John Henry O'Hara was an American writer born in Pottsville, Pennsylvania on January 31, 1905. He was the son of Patrick Henry O'Hara, a surgeon, and Katharine Elizabeth Delaney and was the oldest of eight children. O'Hara attended the Fordham Preparatory School, the Keystone State Normal School, and the Niagara Preparatory School but was dismissed from all three. His desire to attend Yale remained unrealized due to his father's death in 1925, after which O'Hara worked at a variety of jobs that led to journalism and, finally, a career as a writer of novels and short stories. His places of residence included New York, Hollywood, Long Island, and finally Princeton, New Jersey, where he died on April 11, 1970.
O'Hara had a short story first published in the New Yorker in 1928, but it was his 1934 novel Appointment in Samarra that was his first success. With individual short stories continuing to appear in popular periodicals, he published collections and novels such as The Doctor's Son and Other Stories, Butterfield 8, and Pal Joey. Although critical response was and remains mixed, O'Hara's work generally met with commercial success, and some of his efforts were adapted for the stage and screen.
O'Hara married three times, first in 1931 to Helen Ritchie Petit, which ended in divorce in 1933; then in 1937 to Belle Mulford Wylie, with whom he had one child before she passed away in 1954; and finally in 1955 to Katharine Barnes Bryan, who survived him.
Scope and Contents
The papers document a portion of the creative process of writer John O'Hara, 1905-1970. They consist primarily of typed manuscript drafts, galley proofs, and page proofs of individual short stories, collections of stories, and novels, many with manuscript annotations. Some drafts of the collections include previously-printed stories excised from their original print source (often the New Yorker ). The manuscript for "The Ewings" is a photocopy. There is also a small amount of correspondence between O'Hara, James T. Babb, and Robert Hawthorne Wylie. The papers span the range of much of O'Hara's career, from circa 1934 to circa 1970, but represent only a portion of his creative output.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the writings were gifts of John O'Hara in 1944 and 1945. The photocopy of "The Ewings" was a gift of the Book-of-the-Month Club in 1972. The correspondence from John O'Hara to James Babb was a gift of James T. Babb in 1962, while the correspondence from John O'Hara to Robert Wylie was a gift of Robert Hawthorne Wylie.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series I. Writings; and Series II: Correspondence. Series I is organized into two subseries: Short Stories; and Monographs.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors; O'Hara, John, 1905-1970; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Wylie, Robert Hawthorne
- Writings, 1934-1970; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  - SHORT STORIES
    Scope and Contents
    All files contain single typescript drafts with author's manuscript notations, with the exception of Mrs. Whitman, which contains two typescript drafts with author's manuscript notations.
    - Adventure on the Set, 1934 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bread Alone, 1939 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Civilized, 1943 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Graven Image, 1942 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Handler, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Joey and the Calcutta Club, 1939 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Lieutenant, 1943 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Magical Numbers, 1939 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mrs. Whitman, 1945 January (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Alternate title: Ella M. Whitman
    - The Next-to-Last Dance of the Season, 1943 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Nothing Missing, 1939 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Summer's Day, 1942 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Too Young, 1939 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Walter T. Carriman, 1943 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Alternate title: Walter T. Janison
    - Where's the Game, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - MONOGRAPHS
    - Appointment in Samarra, corrected galley proofs, circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Butterfield 8
      All files contain single typescript drafts, with author's manuscript notations in varying frequency.
      - First draft (incomplete), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Intermediate draft (incomplete), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Revised draft, 1935 August 5 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    - The Doctor's Son and Other Stories
      - Draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Galley proofs, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Page proofs, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The Ewings, setting typescript (photocopy), 1970 February 9 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    - Pipe Night, draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, 1956-1962; Series II; 2
  - Babb, James T., 1956-1962 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Wylie, Robert Hawthorne, 1956-1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)